It walked southward.
（観察者）それは南へ歩いていた
It gathered knowledge,
and through stimulation,
それは情報を収集し
刺激を得ることによって
その情報を複製する
it could replicate that information.
（球(きゅう)が落ちる音）
A rock...
（観察者）石…
A wolf...
オオカミ…
And then, a human being.
そして人間
Because it possessed none of the
things that make humans human,
それは人間たらしめるものを
何も持っていないため
it soiled itself and failed to
procure sufficient nourishment.
下(しも)は垂れ流し 栄養補給も
ままならなかった
And so, it died quickly.
そのため すぐ死んだ
To this object, death is
but a change in state.
この物体にとって
死は単なる状態の変化である
It had died six times so far, but it
regenerated, as expected, each time.
ここまで すでに６回 死んだが
再生機能は
すべて正しく動いてくれた
The first time, it took five whole days,
１回目は復活まで
丸５日かかったが
but by the sixth time, it could
accomplish it in roughly twelve hours.
６回目の頃には
12時間程度になった
Pain promotes growth.
痛みは成長を促す
No death is wasted.
ムダな死などない
（鳥の鳴き声）
（オニグマの咆哮(ほうこう)）
It died again.
（観察者）また死んだ
But that was not a problem.
だが問題はない
♪～
～♪
Mommy, I'm so hungry, I could die!
（マーチ）“グ～…
おなか空いて死にそうだよ ママ”
Oh, Usajiro, you poor baby!
あらあら ウサじろうったら
かわいそうに
Mommy will make you something right away.
ママがゴハン作ってあげるわね
There you go. Eat up.
できたわ！　お食べ
Yummy!
“おいしい さすがママ
料理上手だね”
Thank you, Mommy!
You're so good at cooking!
Oh, my, thank you!
あらまあ！　ありがとう…
ん？
Congratulations, Lee.
（リーの祖母）
おめでとう リー
You're a full-fledged adult now, eh?
（リーの祖母）
これで立派な大人だね
Thanks, Grandma.
（リー）
ありがとう おばあちゃん
ん？
あ…
What are you looking at, March?
（パロナ）何を見てる マーチ？
ん？
Ta-da!
What's this?
（パロナ）
じゃん！　これ なーんだ？
We had another baby?!
生まれたのね！
That's right.
そうだ 六男のカニ太郎！
Our sixth child, Kanitaro!
I've been wanting another child!
（マーチ）うわー ちょうど
子供が欲しかったのよ
Now we're a family of eight!
これで８人家族ね
That's right.
そうだな
Here, darling! Eat this feast
I made to thank you!
あなた ありがとうの
ごちそう食べて！
Wow, this looks delicious!
わあ！　おいしそうだ
You always make the best food, honey.
やっぱ お前の作ったメシは最高だ
Aren't you glad you married me?
（マーチ）ウフッ あたしと
結婚してよかったでしょ？
Time to eat, March.
（マーチの父親）メシだぞ マーチ
Daddy! Mommy!
パパ！　ママ！
Look! Kanitaro!
見て！　カニ太郎！
She made a new one, eh? Very nice.
（父親）おっ 新作か いいねえ
Thank you for looking after her
all the time, Parona-chan.
（マーチの母親）いつも悪いわね
パロナちゃん
Not at all.
いえ マーチといると
心が落ちつくんです
Being around March comforts me.
Hey, Mommy, when do I get to be a grown-up?
（マーチ）ねえ ママ
マーチは いつになったら
大人になれるのかしら
That question again?
また その質問か
Once you stop wetting the bed,
then sleep 3,000 times more.
オネショをなくしてから
3000回 眠った頃
That's what I always tell you.
そう言ってるでしょ
I can't wait that long!
そんなに待てないわ！
I wanna grow up so I can be a mommy!
早く大人になって
ママになりたいんだもの
Did you know? Lee-chan next
door isn't a child anymore!
知ってる？　隣のリーちゃん
もう子供じゃなくなったって！
They took the ink off her face!
お顔の墨が取れてたわ
The only children left in this village
are me, Lisa, and little Lalah!
この村で子供なの あとはマーチと
リサとチビのラーラくらいよ
It's so humiliating!
恥ずかしいわ
There, there, Lisa.
どれ リサや 今度は
お姉ちゃんがオッパイあげよう
Let me feed you some of my milk.
Stop that.
やめなさい
Let me tell you a secret, March.
いいこと教えてやるぞ マーチ
ん？
Now, listen. You can't become
a grown-up if you don't behave.
いいか おとなしくしないと
大人になれないんだぞ
Hush up to grow up!
“おとな”だけにな
What?! That's so silly!
何それ！　意味分かんなーい
（３人の笑い声）
A Rambunctious Girl
（鳥のさえずり）
ハァ…
That bow is too strong and heavy for you.
（村の男性）その弓
お前には重くて強すぎるんだよ
Don't worry. You'll get
better at it eventually.
（村の男性）大丈夫！
いつか うまくなるって
We'll help you out.
（村の男性）俺らも協力するからさ
がんばって練習しようぜ
Let's hang in there and keep practicing.
Thanks.
ありがとう
Hey, where's Daddy?
（マーチ）
ねえ パパは？　パパは？
Where's Daddy?
Daddy's busy with work.
パパは お仕事で忙しいの
Aw, but...
えー でも…
Now, don't be selfish!
わがままダメ
（半鐘のような音）
ん？　何の音かしらね
What's that sound?
I don't know.
“知らなーい”
March!
（パロナ）マーチ！
（マーチ）え？
ハァハァハァ…
Sissy!
ねーね！
Where are we going?
（マーチ）どこ行くの？
I found a nice spot.
（パロナ）いい場所 見つけたんだ
今日は そこで遊ぼう
Let's go play there today.
What do you think you're doing?
（ハヤセ）何をしているのですか？
あ…
That girl is from the village, is she not?
（ハヤセ）それは村の娘でしょう？
Did you not hear the order to assemble?
集合命令を
聞いていなかったのですか？
う… くっ
ん？
Rejoice, everyone.
（ハヤセ）皆さん 喜んでください
Your village was fortunate enough
to be chosen this year.
今年は幸運にも
この村が選ばれました
The ritual of gratitude to Oniguma-sama,
the god who brings peace
ニナンナ地域の安泰と繁栄を
与えてくれる神
and prosperity to the Ninannah region,
オニグマ様への感謝の儀式を
この村で行うのです
will be held in this village.
In accordance with tradition,
we, the Yanome people,
オニグマ様へ ささげる
穢(けが)れのない少女
（リサをあやす声）
will choose an untarnished girl
to offer to Oniguma-sama.
その選出は伝統にのっとり
我々ヤノメ人が行います
Let's see...
（ラーラ）ん？
（ピオラン）どれ…
（ピオラン）ふん…
ふん…
ヒャハハ…
（マーチ）ん？
ヘヘッ
んあ～…
アハハ
（ピオラン）ふん…
This is the one.
この子だ
Congratulations, March!
（村人）おめでとう マーチ
Congratulations!
（村人たち）
おめでとう おめでとう
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
Why are they congratulating
me? What happened?
“おめでとう”って何かあったの？
You were chosen for a great honor.
あなたは とても名誉なことに
選ばれたのよ
Honor?
めいよ？
（マーチ）エヘヘ…
We're so sorry, March!
ごめんなさい マーチ
ど… どうしたの ママ？
What's wrong, Mommy?
You are going to die.
（ハヤセ）あなたは死ぬのです
マーチさん
March-san.
え？
You are to be sacrificed to Oniguma-sama.
オニグマ様へ ささげる
いけにえとなるのです
For all of our sakes.
みんなのために
Sacrificed?
いけにえ？
My name is Hayase.
わたくし ハヤセと申します
I have been ordered to look after
you until the ritual is complete.
儀式が完了するまでの間
世話役を務めるよう
命じられています
Move back, please.
（父親）あっ
（ハヤセ）離れてください
No men may come near her.
男性が近づいては なりません
We must not allow her to be tarnished.
穢れを寄せつけては
いけないのです
Here is the schedule.
スケジュールを伝えます
On the day before we leave,
the village will hold a banquet.
出発前日に村全体で宴を行います
The family is asked to say
their goodbyes at this time.
家族の皆さんは ここで
お別れを済ませてください
We will then spend three days
climbing the mountain.
山へは３日かけて登ります
You two may rest assured
that we will travel safely.
十分 安全に気をつけて進むので
お二人は安心なさってください
March-san will sleep on the
altar atop the mountain.
マーチさんには山の祭壇で
眠ってもらいます
We will return down the mountain
before Oniguma-sama arrives.
私たちはオニグマ様を待たずに
山を下(お)り
In one year, we will retrieve
anything that remains on the altar
１年後 祭壇に残っているものを
回収して
and bring it home to the parents.
ご両親に お返しします
I don't wanna die, though!
マーチ 死にたくないんだけど
If I die, I can't become a grown-up, right?
死ぬって大人になれないって
ことでしょ？
That would be the case.
そうですね
So I don't want to die!
だから死にたくないんだけど
That is unfortunate.
残念ですね
えいっ
Why do you get to decide what happens to me?!
なんでマーチのこと
勝手に決めるのよ！
That is the tradition.
そういう決まりです
What?! That doesn't make sense!
はあ？　意味分かんないし！
No! No! No!
ヤダヤダヤダ 死にたくなーい
I don't want to die!
Why do I have to die?!
なんでマーチだけ
死なないといけないのよ？
Why don't I get to become a grown-up?!
なんでマーチだけ
大人になれないのよ！
Tell me! Why?! Why?! Why?!
ねえ なんでなんでなんで…
March!
（父親）マーチ！
Behave.
おとなしく…
March-chan, eat this.
（村の女性）マーチちゃん これを
Eat this, too.
（村の女性）これも食べて
Lalah.
ラーラ
I made this, March.
（ラーラ）マーチ これ作ったの
Wear it on your last day.
最後の日に着けて
Thanks.
ありがとう… がんばるわ 私
I'll do my best.
Is your job to watch me go to the bathroom?
あなたの仕事って
マーチのトイレの観察？
I am watching over you until the final day
to ensure you remain in pristine condition.
最後の日まで
あなたが万全の状態でいられるよう
見守っているのです
You're making sure I don't run away.
逃げないように見てるのね
Allow me to warn you: if you run away,
忠告しておきますが
あなたが逃げたら
Lalah will die in your place.
代わりにラーラが死にますよ
And if Lalah runs away?
ラーラが逃げたら？
We will choose the one who can't run away.
逃げられない あの子を選びます
（リサの泣き声）
Oh, dear. What's wrong?
（母親）あらあら どうしたの？
（リサの泣き声）
There, there.
（母親）よしよし はい
よしよし よしよし…
（嗚咽）
（村人たちの泣き声）
You have been very strong.
（ハヤセ）今日まで
よくがんばりましたね
ん？
You are behaving well.
おとなしくできたじゃないですか
立派ですよ
I'm impressed.
There is a legend that says freedom
awaits in the world after death.
こんな言い伝えがあるんです
死んだ先の世界では
自由が待っている
You can do anything and become anything.
何でもやれるし 何にでもなれる
There, you can become the grown-up
that you could not become here.
そこでは ここでなれなかった
大人にだってなれるんです
（鳥が飛び立つ音）
（矢が放たれる音）
あっ
（従者たち）おっ
An arrow...
（ハヤセ）矢…
She got away!
（従者たち）あっ
（従者）逃げたぞ！
Hold it!
待ちなさい！
Hayase-sama!
（従者）ハヤセ様！
After March!
Don't lose her!
マーチを追え 逃がすな！
ハァハァハァ…
あっ！　わっ おっ とっ
うわっ
She disappeared?
（従者）消えた？　そっち捜せ！
Search over there!
She's not here!
Search harder!
（従者）いないぞ よく捜せ
プハッ ハァハァハァ…
I'm sorry, Daddy.
（マーチ）ごめんなさい パパ
I couldn't behave.
マーチ おとなしくなれなかった
フゥ ハァハァ…
あ…
ん？　あ…
わっ
（マーチ）あ…
There she is! It's March!
（従者）いたぞ マーチだ！
（驚く声）
What is that?!
（従者）何だ あれは！
W-Wait for me!
（従者）わああ…
（従者）待ってくれ
あ…
What?
何？
What is this?
これ 何？
U-Um...
あ… あの…
ひぇ！
あ…
Where are you going?
どこ行くの？
む…
Take me with you!
マーチも連れていって！
I see.
なるほど マーチさんの死を
偽装するつもりでしたか
You were going to fake March-san's death.
I see what you were trying to do,
but it was like a child playing pretend.
やりたいことは分かりましたが
まるで ごっこ遊びでしたね
Do not misunderstand.
I will not be the one to punish you.
勘違いしないでくださいね
お前を罰するのは私ではなく
It will be your own people of Ninannah.
あなた方 ニナンナの人々です
（草をかき分ける音）
（従者たち）ハァハァハァ…
Where's March?
（ハヤセ）マーチは？
Well...
（従者）いや それが…
You let her get away?
（ハヤセ）逃がしたのですか？
Let's go back to the village
and get another girl.
（従者）村に帰って
代わりの子を連れてこよう
We will find her before
we humiliate ourselves!
（ハヤセ）そんな恥をかく前に
見つけるんだよ！
Get back to searching at once!
今すぐ捜し直すぞ！
No! Wait!
（従者）ダメだ 待ってくれ！
There's a monster out there!
（従者）バケモノがいるんだ
A monster?
バケモノ？
What are you?
あなたって何なの？
You looked like an empty husk at first.
最初は抜け殻さんに見えたのに
Then you went all squiggly,
and you came back to life.
ウニョニョってなって
生き返ったように見えたわ
One time, Sissy stepped on a bug and it
came back to life, and it scared me.
前にね ねーねが踏んづけたのに
生きてた虫がいて
うわーってなったの
Isn't that called... uh... in... imm...
確か ああいうのって…
ふし… ふじみ…
Immortal, right?
不死身っていうんでしょ？
Sissy taught me.
ねーねが教えてくれたわ
By the way, where did you come from?
そういえば どこから来たの？
Not Ninannah, right? And you don't
look like you're from Yanome...
ニナンナじゃないもんね
ヤノメっぽくもないし…
What's your name?
あなた 名前は？
Mine's March!
私はマーチっていうの！
Hey! Say something!
ねえ 何か答えてよ！
おしゃべり できないの？
Don't you know how to talk?!
（フシ）ハッ
ん？　あ…
That fruit looks sweet.
甘そうな果物
Yeah, I'm getting hungry, too.
（マーチおなかが鳴る音）
そうね おなかも
空いてきたことだし…
I'll get some for you!
取ってあげる！
Leave this to me! I'm a good climber!
任して 木登りは得意よ
Here!
はい！
うわっ
うわ… えー ウソでしょ
You've gotta be kidding...
You poor thing.
かわいそうに
親に しつけられなかったのね
Your parents must not have
taught you manners.
ゲプッ
Here.
You eat with your hands, like this.
ほら こうやって
手で持って食べるのよ
うわあ！
You're so awful!
まあ なんて人！
For crying out loud...
まったくもう…
ああ…
You're mean! That was mine!
ひどいわ マーチの分なのに！
Sheesh...
もう…
No! These are mine!
ダメよ マーチの… ああ！
ん…
むばああああ！
（マーチの泣きじゃくる声）
ハァハァハァ…
ふんっ
ふんふんふんふんっ
（ゲップ）
Were you that hungry?
そんなに食べたかったの？
Listen. When someone you don't
know does something nice for you,
いい？　知らない人に
親切にしてもらったら
you have to say "thank you," okay?
ありがとうって言わないとダメよ
Can you say that? Say "thank you."
言える？
ほら “ありがとう”って
"Thank you."
“あ… り… が… と… う”
Thank you.
“ありがとう”
あっ
Hey!
Don't just walk away!
ちょっと！　勝手に行かないで
ん…
You're going to sleep?
寝るの？
Hey.
おーい
モグモグ… はむっ
（マーチの寝息）
Mommy! Daddy!
ママ！　パパ！
マーチ戻ってきたよ
I'm home!
March!
（母親･父親）マーチ
アハッ
ん？　あれ リサは？
Huh?
Where's Lisa?
あっ
あ…
It's your fault, March.
お前のせいだ マーチ
Sissy...
（マーチ）ねーね…
They were sacrificed because you ran away.
（パロナ）お前が逃げたせいで
あの２人が いけにえに
ハッ！
ハァハァハァハァ…
うっ うう…
（鳥のさえずり）
ん？
Wh-What's the matter?
Why are you following me?
ど… どうしたの？　ついてきて
ふんっ
ええ？
む…
あ…
Sheesh...
もう！　マーチは
あんたのママじゃないんだからね！
I'm not your mommy, you know!
♪～
～♪
Preview
A boy who knows nothing, and March,
who acts like a loving mother to her son.
（観察者）何も知らない少年と
わが子を愛でる母親のように
振る舞うマーチ
The two interact, little by little.
２人は少しずつ交流を重ねてゆく
Parona struggles to save March.
マーチの命を救おうと抗うパロナ
Hayase pursues March relentlessly.
執拗(しつよう)に追い詰めるハヤセ
And a giant shadow emerges.
そして現れる巨大な影…
A Small Evolution